[Music]
what's up everyone
i hope you're as excited as i am to talk
a whole bunch about muscle hypertrophy
before we get started i need to
apologize i know my voice sounds a bit
weird
i've just been dealing with a couple of
weeks of a very very nasty case of the
gains yeah i know
you loved it well if you like my friend
chris here
and you like me right every one of us
that i know is interested in some point
to maximizing their muscle gains and you
may be thinking to yourself
hey andy i know that muscle physiology
is your area of expertise you study
how muscle fibers grow shrink dye and
repair in your lab and you've been doing
that for a decade
but you may not realize i actually used
to be a competitive bodybuilder
back in the day in fact i was actually
pretty famous before there was even
instagram in those things and
i used to get fans come up to me all the
time asking me for pictures and you can
see like a good example that here this
guy right up was like hey man can i get
a double biceps picture and i'm like
sure
you know so i was kind enough to take a
picture of him with it and
um you know anyways if you
you want to actually see a picture of me
my one of my competitions all right well
here it is i was a little more tan and
just a little
a little bit more muscular in this
picture here but this is
this is a local meet that i did one time
i didn't win you know obviously
i thought i got second place so it was
pretty good
well anyways uh and humans in general
we've been interested in strength
training and gaining muscle
for a really long time in fact there's
documents suggesting that we've been
lifting muscle
or lifting weights for the purpose of
growing muscle since the 7th century
there's a really cool article here by
the famous
sport historian jan todd on the history
of barbells and dumbbells and when women
started lifting with dumbbells and
things like that that
i encourage you to explore but we've
actually been studying muscle growth
with exercise for almost 100 or over 100
years now
the first study came out in the late
1800s
by a german scientist and he actually
threw a couple of dogs
on a treadmill what he did is he
actually cut one of those sartorius
muscles out of their leg
put them on a treadmill for two months
and then looked at how much
their other assault areas grew and found
about a 50
increase in hypertrophy after just
treadmill running for a couple of months
so the point being we've spent a lot of
time and effort
as a society as scientists and as
individuals
trying to understand how to maximize
muscle growth for a very long time
and if you've been up to date with the
field or you've seen any of my previous
work
especially some of my podcasts with
barbell shrugged and stuff years ago
you may feel like you got a pretty good
grip on the science but what i want to
actually do and the reason
i'm making all these videos is we have
learned a tremendous amount in the last
three years alone
on what muscle hypertrophy actually is
what causes it
and then how to then maximize it with
your training and hypertrophy
so i've decided to do this giant video
series on all things hypertrophy
in part one like i said i'll describe
some of the newest things we've learned
in just the last couple of years in fact
several of the things i've included in
that video came out just within a month
of me filming this
so i'll talk in depth about what we know
uh scientifically
about what actually is muscle
hypertrophy what parts grow which ones
don't how much
etc part two then i'll get into the
stimuli and it causes the molecular
mechanisms
if you like the biochemistry piece the
molecular biology side of it
video two is your jam and then part
three is when i'll specifically get into
the eating and training to maximize
so if you just want the practical
applications you want to know how much
volume you should be hitting what order
to do your exercises in
frequency uh what type e center
concentric
drop sets pyramids which ones work
better all that stuff
that's all in video three but i actually
i think you should start with at least
video two because
you'll never really truly understand uh
how to train
to optimize growth if you don't
understand what's causing
your body to want to grow muscle in the
first place
um well what i'll also do is i'll try to
chop these up into some five-minute ones
as well but
if you want the full jam my strongest
recommendation start at one go to two
go to three and you'll all understand as
much as we could possibly give you
on all things muscle hypertrophy okay
enjoy let's have a fun ride here and
let's get a little bit more
jacked all right maybe i should stop i
don't know when i look better
i'm dr andy galpin this is 55 minute
fizz and you're about to learn
everything you ever wanted to know about
the science
of getting jet all right now this is
part three
in my epic three-part series on all
things muscle hypertrophy
in part one if you missed that i covered
the latest breaking science we have
on the physiology of hypertrophy so what
part of the muscle grows
what's that actually mean the cell the
molecular stuff
all that in part two then we talked
about the stimuli so what has to happen
in your body
to stimulate muscle growth because we
did that that set us up
in a fantastic way to understand part
three
which is what you're all after right so
we know what grows what are we going
after
we know what stimulates it and what
causes it so now how do i have to eat
and how do i train to maximize that now
if you're one of the many many people
who've jumped straight to video three
here
and you went right past videos one and
two
shame on you the inner muscle nerd in me
is crying okay how dare you not want to
spend a couple of hours learning the
biochemistry
and molecular physiology of what's
happening inside the tissue that causes
your growth
you just want to know what to eat and
how to train you're breaking my heart
i can't believe you do this to me after
all we've done together this is how you
do me
but that's okay so what are we going to
talk about specifically before you're
about to commit to these next at this
next hour or so
i'll share it here's our outline for
what we're going to get into okay
starting off we'll get you the eating
first we'll talk about calories macros
protein
post-exercise anabolic window all that
stuff and then we're going to save the
bulk of our conversation
today on the training stuff okay now if
in case i forget to mention this later i
do have a lot of other videos for
example on the exercise
post exercise anabolic window a lot of
nutrition videos so i'm going to keep
that section fairly short today
so we can dive into things like how
heavy do i lift
how many reps do i do how much volume
per week do i train to failure
rest intervals exercise order um why
renaissance periodization the company
as well as the people in it every one of
those people suck yeah they're all
awful we're going to talk about that
we'll talk about
what range of motion should you go
partial or all the way up and down
eccentrics consciousness
how about time under tension tempo what
about time of the day
morning noon night should i train when
my growth hormone's highest does that
matter
we'll talk about hard gainers what's
going on there and then we'll finish
with what i call little potpourri little
surprise
and we'll see what that is all right so
if you're still around
great fantastic top up that coffee get
some extra water and let's go
let's get started with the nutrition
side of things now this is actually an
article that i strongly encourage you
all go and read
if you want to know more about
maximizing the nutrition of maximized
hypertrophy it's right there the title
right
great work by alan and brad here okay
but i'm going to give it to you in the
condensed version
just now here are some of the things
that we know that are pretty central to
maximizing muscle growth
and the first is you've got to be in
some sort of caloric surplus
what this means is say you eat 2 000
calories a day just to make our math
easy and you've been doing that for the
last two or three months and that pretty
much keeps you at the same body size in
other words total weight
200 pounds or whatever as well as the
same body composition so the same amount
of fat
and muscle well we know that if you want
to grow muscle you've got to
add some calories and one of the major
mistakes folks make while doing this is
they add way too many calories
okay we had low quality foods as well as
way too high so instead of going
from 2000 calories to say 2200
which would be only 200 additional
calories doesn't seem like enough but
that's a 10
increase folks will go to things like 3
000 or even 4 000. i've seen like 5 000
doubling tripling of calories
well here's what we know about that yes
of course
the more calories you consume the more
weight you will gain but as you continue
to
increase this caloric surplus most
likely what's happening
is you reduce the percentage of weight
that you gain coming from muscle in
other words
if you go on that 2000 calorie day diet
and you increase by
10 and so you go to 2200 after
say two months you might put on five
pounds of muscle and one pound of fat
it's pretty
difficult to put on only muscle in a
caloric surplus
but what we're just trying to do is
hedge our bets to gain the highest
percentage of lean tissue is what we'll
call it versus non-lean tissue
it's never going to be a pure lean
tissue game thing however if you were to
take that number
and then go to one of those crazy things
like three thousand you might instead of
gaining five pounds of muscle you might
gain more you might gain seven or eight
pounds a month
but you'll probably also gain four five
six maybe eight pounds of fat as well
and so it's not that you can't gain as
much
more calories you'll gain more muscle
but the percentage of it coming from
lean tissue
starts to really go down so therefore
should you make sure you stay at only
that 10
number not necessarily it depends on
your goal if you're just trying to add
as much mass as possible
well then you may go to 20 25 percent
maybe even slightly higher in fact
we have some indirect evidence not a ton
but some
it indicates beginners probably can get
away with more like a 15 to 20 percent
caloric surplus just in general and
still be gaining fairly lean tissue
now we need a lot more research in this
area i know eric helms
in new zealand and some other folks are
looking into this
so you know i may change my answer here
but i told you at the beginning of this
video this is about the latest breaking
science
so this is what we know right now okay
this isn't what we've been talking about
in textbooks for the last 15 years
so if you were to continue to add that
those calories in and you got to that 20
30 40 50 60
increase in calories above your
maintenance calories you're most likely
going to be adding a higher percentage
of
non-lean tissue if you're just trying to
maximize your growth you maybe don't
care maybe you're a bodybuilder and
you're 10 months away from season or
maybe you're even
three or four years away from when
you're trying to peak you're just trying
to add as much muscle as possible you
don't care
if you're not trying to maximize your
growth for competition's sake and you
you literally are just trying to add as
much lean tissue as possible
well then you may want to stick to these
lower kind of numbers
and it seems small i know but i promise
you that extra 300 calories a day or
whatever it ends up being
it's going to be enough to help you grow
you just have to be a little bit
patient okay so check mark number one
gotta have the calories there thing
number two
okay how many of these calories how do i
break them up what in other words what
are my macros look like within my
calories
well the carbohydrates people tend to
grow pretty well
in this four to seven grams per kilogram
body weight range
now i won't think it will tell you
because fat's coming up here next
i don't think the ratio between fat and
carbohydrate
matter that much i mean unless you get
to some extreme ends okay
but on a normal mixed macronutrient diet
the real key here
is protein so as long as your total
calories are appropriate and your total
protein is appropriate
if you like to go a little bit higher on
the carbohydrate scale and a little bit
lower on the fat scale
or the inverse i cannot imagine it
really matters
at the group level that much maybe if
you feel like that works better for you
well they're fantastic but for general
recommendations land somewhere in this
neighborhood
so some folks i know will go closer to
like one and a half grams per kilogram
of fat
but because of that if you don't want
your total calories to get completely
out of whack
then you got to bring your carbohydrates
down a little bit keep in mind another
little trick here that eludes people a
lot of times
carbohydrate and protein have the same
number of calories per gram
so both four but fat is over double that
nine
so if you increase your grams of fat
just a little bit you're actually over
doubling your calories so just be
careful of that okay
and again not that going high fat is bad
for you especially when you're trying to
go in caloric surplus just
don't let the numbers run away from you
okay you think you're in a 10 surplus
you're actually in a 35 percent one
you may have a different response than
you anticipate okay so just be aware
that's all i care about and then make
your
decision appropriately so let's go talk
a little bit more about the protein
one thing that we know is again also
we're not talking about what is
theoretically possible at the lower
limits
so can do you have to have a minimum of
two grams per kilogram body weight
which would be almost the same as saying
one gram per pound if you prefer that
system
just a little bit lower than that do you
have to have that high to grow muscle
no you don't have to we're talking about
what's probably going to optimize the
growth process in most people
and so what we can actually see is and
if you look at jose antonio's work and
he's published several studies now
you can even go really high four grams
five grams per kilogram so he's doubled
or tripled the recommendation and still
sees
pretty high increases in lean tissue and
so protein is the one or i would say is
like if you're not paying a super strong
detail to your carbs and fat
like okay but just make sure you're
hitting these protein numbers and hedge
on the side of too much
error on the side of a little bit more
protein than a little bit less
all right it's not going to be um it's
not going to add a lot of fat tissue
it's very difficult to convert protein
into
into fat you're not going to do that
it's very transient as well
carbohydrate and protein or carbohydrate
fats stay around and they're easy to
store and reuse
energy protein is very transient so it
has to be there in the cell when the
signal is hot for growing
i described all that in part two if
you're like what the hell are you
talking about
that was part two of the video of the
series part
video two of this series so the protein
won't though it's transient it's gonna
go and go out right so you gotta make
sure that stuff is hot there so i would
have strongly recommend staying
up pretty strong on your protein
okay within that let's talk a little bit
more about the protein
what we really want to shoot for is
somewhere in the neighborhood of
and depending on the place you look 0.25
up to 0.4 grams of high quality protein
per feeding
i like the 0.4 number better some people
say 0.2
0.3 this translates into roughly 20 to
50 grams
of total protein per feeding and so if
you're breaking that up and say you're
eating four times a day or three times a
day with a snack
and you have 50 grams of protein per
meal for your three meals that'd be 150
grams maybe have a
30 gram snack that puts you at 180 for a
200 pound person you'd be hitting pretty
close to that 2 grams per kilogram
number or you know a little bit less
than one gram per pound now i think
that's the low end i think you should
try to get a lot higher than that
again if you want to maximize it also
because there's really no downside to it
right there's very little
issues with going higher in protein and
potential to help so
so why not okay now what do we mean we
say high quality protein
high quality protein are the the ones
that typically contain
all the essential amino acids and we
know that those ones specifically
influence muscle growth non-essential
amino acids do not so
you can't just look at your total
protein number you have to look at the
high quality one so those are
the ones that come in the complete
protein form or
food combinations that come with
complete proteins either way is fine
all right but they have to be able to be
digested and assimilated fairly quickly
and efficiently we also have to make
sure that we're doing that
with efficient efficiency per calorie
okay so something that maybe for example
if you took uh
peanut butter and you say okay there's
some protein in it but
in order to get the same amount of
protein as you'd get in say a chicken
breast
you'd have to triple the calories and so
you would run out of your calories
really fast in order to get the same
amount of protein
and that would put you way too high of a
caloric excess so that's not a high
quality protein source even though
quote unquote there is some protein in
it okay that's not really what we're
looking for that's not how we define a
high quality protein
okay so within that you want to hit
somewhere in the neighborhood of seven
to three thousand milligrams of leucine
per feeding three grams of leucine is
how we would typically say
it combined with other essential amino
acids and three grams of leucine
is pretty standard in a 30 gram
load of whole complete protein so if
you're eating high quality protein
and you're eating enough i guess is the
take-home here then you're gonna get
that leucine threshold
and the research is pretty clear here
once you pass that threshold of leucine
in other words this three three grams
number
adding any more leucine doesn't give you
any more growth and that's why we call
it a threshold okay
so once you cross that threshold you're
good to go
so if you want to get to the detail here
and you want to use myfitnesspal and you
want to look up how much
protein and how much leucine is in all
your protein sources you can
or you can just say i'm gonna at least
hit a gram per pound of high quality
um mostly whole food based right so we
don't want to start supplements we can
use
on top but we want to get this from
whole foods the reason being
when you get it from whole foods you get
all those essential amino acids
if it's a complete protein source so you
don't necessarily get that in
supplements
and a barrage of other reasons that i'm
not going to get into now so
if you just hit those big total protein
values from high quality sources
you're probably going to take care of
your leucine if you're doing that
frequently
you're going to be just fine now i don't
want to have time to get too much more
into this but
since we're kind of talking about this
it is a bit unclear well i'll back up it
is fairly clear actually
that you don't have to have six meals a
day you don't have to have seven or
eight meals a day
if you hit your numbers and across three
meals
then it's probably pretty similar to six
meals in terms of just maximizing growth
what about if it's a single meal well
now i think you're gonna start running
into some problems okay now we are
missing some research in terms of
hypertrophy with things like
intermittent fasting and some other
manipulations we just haven't done
that research yet so i don't know all i
can say is
it looks like it's fine whether or not
it's actually in
you know two or three or four versus
five or six or seven that probably
doesn't matter that much
for most people so you can kind of play
with this stuff
however you'd like
that being said um i can't pass this
opportunity to talk a little bit about
the anabolic window before we leave our
discussion on eating
for maximizing hypertrophy i have a
whole video on this i think it's 25
minutes
but the quick version is kind of like i
just laid out
you need to have nutrients available
during
the the growth process so when the the
signaling cascade is as high as like i
described in video number two
but that doesn't mean you have to have a
protein shake within 60 minutes or even
a couple of hours after your workout it
depends on the context of your situation
are you training fasted in the morning
are you training it in the evening after
you've already had
200 grams of protein in your system all
of these things influence
the importance or relevance of the
anabolic window but it does exist
yeah it does exist whether you care
about it though
is sort of a different story so go over
and check out that video if you want to
learn more about the anabolic window
okay that's all the time we have to
cover the nutrition i wanted to give you
the bare minimum so at least you had
something
to work off of there let's spend the
rest of the time talking about the
training recommendations
for that so when we talk about
programming for exercise
we use this acronym called kofoverp and
that stands for what we collectively
refer to as your modifiable variables so
these are the things that you can change
in your workouts that will alter the
adaptation you get
in the context of hypertrophy that
typically comes down to these
variables the exercise choice so what
exercise you use
within that we would also talk about you
know what ranges of motion you would do
what um you know concentric eccentric
and then
the different ways you can manipulate
the exercise itself
your foot the foot placement the hand
placement all that other stuff okay
we'll talk about your rest intervals
which are the rest you take in between
sets the intensity so the percentage of
your one rep max the order that you do
the exercises in
as well as the frequency being how many
times per week you hit that muscle
so in the next 40 minutes or so however
long this takes me i'm gonna go
through the latest science on all of
these variables so you know how to
manipulate them to optimize your
likelihood of growing
but having said that the reason i have
this one starred in the bottom
is it's very clear at this point
scientifically the vast majority of
hypertrophy is being driven by volume
so we have to spend most of our time
there and we're going to start there
first
let's dive in now
it is very clear at this point despite
what you might want to watch and when
you're hoping to hear me say
but there is no one single best
recommendation
there is no one uh number of reps you
have to get to or total sets to get to
per week
in fact the spectrum is pretty high
that's kind of why i i honestly for
years have been avoiding doing this
video
because the topic has always bored me
frankly because it's kind of idiot proof
i'm like geez just get anywhere between
here and here and you get the same
amount of growth so like how much real
time do you want to spend
diving into the differences between here
and here when at the end it all results
in the same outcome
and that's now because we have more
research not only is that clear
but we also know why it's because all
you have to do is get to a certain
threshold of stimuli
to cause this cascade of muscle growth
and the result is going to be the same
the analogy i'll give you is
with kind of like a light switch so
imagine you had a switch in your room
not a dimmer just an on off switch and
once you flick that thing
on you can keep pressing the button up
if you want
but it's not going to get any brighter
once the signal is maximized
that's as high as it goes and it turns
out that's exactly how muscle
hypertrophy works there's only
such a so high of a rate of growth you
can get
and it doesn't actually take that much
to eclipse that
and to turn that thing on i described in
the video
a whole bunch of scenarios right you
could get it through low volume
high intensity training you could get it
through the opposite right high reps
ladder rest there's all kinds of
combinations as long as the total volume
and the stimuli get there
the result will be the same so again
this is why it was critically important
we described and discussed
all the different stimuli because you
can go back now and say okay i want to
use this type of training i want to use
this type of training
i know it works through a different
mechanism so the stimulus on the muscles
different but the net result
same amount of growth and now you can
take the context of your situation and
your client
your preferences and whatever else is
going on and deploy
different strategies of training knowing
that if the signal is maximized
we're good to go all right
the analogy i'll give you is this right
if i said hey come up with an equation
that equals 100.
either way it's going to equal 100 and
you could you would i gave you three
examples here but there would be
literally
unlimited almost not literally i hate
when people do that not literally
there's a number the number is large
it's very very large
of the combinations of different numbers
it'd be basically unlimited
that you could use to get to 100.
hypertrophy training is pretty similar
okay now i'll encourage you to go watch
some of my speed or power strength
training videos because it's not so
simple when it comes to those ones so i
don't typically call those ones idiot
proof like i call
hypertrophy training right so summarize
it you just gotta accumulate work
that's it now that being said let's
still dive into each one of these
variables in just a little bit more
detail
and we'll start off with this first most
important one volume
okay so here's what we know that most of
the research is dedicated to figuring
out the ideal volume
in terms of sets per week per muscle
group
okay so think about this not as as in
how many reps i need to accomplish or
uh how many workouts i have to do for
the muscle but again how many sets
per muscle group per week and we know
that this is the primary driver of the
gains as i call it here
and it the how much volume you need to
hit this sort of depends on your basic
level of training coming into it
so for example here's what we generally
will think the research would show for
folks that are kind of untrained or
moderately trained or even completely
sedentary
a couple of interesting things to note
here number one we
typically would say that around 10 sets
per week per muscle
is a good starting place well we do know
it looks like
more will be better in this case at
least up to say even maybe 20
and to be honest we don't necessarily
know that that 20 is
in fact a true peak okay we're actually
kind of missing some research on that
end of the spectrum
and so what we see happen is either the
rate of increase in terms of muscle
growth
either tapers down there or even drops
off
and so if we go from say five sets per
week to 10 sets per week to 15 sets per
week
we probably will see still see content
continual increases in growth
so what we call a dose response
relationship there however at some
point it's going to taper off and
eventually go down you're going to be
fighting against yourself so
that's why we say 10 seems to be
probably a fairly reasonable place to
start
you know you know you can probably most
people can handle more than five sets
per muscle per week
i mean if you think about it this way if
you went and did bicep curls did three
sets of ten
you know monday three sets of ten
thursday that's six sets per week
so so ten sounds may sound like but it's
really not that hard to get to
and so it's probably enough to where an
untrained or
lowly trained person can still recover
plenty and it's also enough to stimulate
growth
is it maximal as an optimal i don't
think so but i'm
always very conservative when it comes
to starting a new training
routine for anybody or in this case
their first
training routine or only training
routine so somewhere in that
neighborhood
if you want to scooch it up to 12 so you
can do three sets three days a week
hey you're probably fine there that'll
be nine right but
you wanna do a couple of them four days
a week whatever you're probably good
but you can be fine uh if you have
someone who can only stay trained once
per week
i don't think i'd hit him with ten sets
but you might if you could split up in
two workouts five sets one week
or monday five sets thursday or
something
that's probably very reasonable to get
to
what we also know is the bottom end of
the spectrum okay we've seen folks
do fine in terms of their maintenance
with as little as five sets per week
now when it comes to tr people that are
trained and by training again i don't
mean you've been working out hard for
six months
probably a few years if not more of
pretty consistent hard training
similar concept right but we see that
the range is quite a bit extended in
fact
it's probably in the neighborhood of 20
to 25 sets per week
before we start to get the optimal range
of growth for the trained individuals
so again if you wanted to be a little
more conservative and you want to start
in the 20
sets per week range that's probably a
good place but you will
most likely want to progress to 25 to
30. now within both of these groups and
i'll talk about this a little bit later
when i get to the hard gainers
but you do want to pay attention to
individual differences some folks that
are really trained
can only handle 15 sets per week and
they just can't get past that recovery
other folks maybe 25s enough you might
they might recover fine actual fact i
have one professional athlete who's
he's very much in the 30 or so per week
range
and he still recovers just fine so he
needs more volume
he needs a lot of doses to see the same
response to somebody who maybe only
needs 20 cents
so some rough numbers to get there now i
will describe in a few more slides about
how this is kind of difficult to
calculate
right so you're probably not going to do
25 sets of bicep curls
all week but you might do 15 sets and
then you want to do another five sets of
maybe various pulling movements that are
not primary to the bicep a secondary
so things get a little bit hairy there
in terms of actually
you know figuring out the volume but
that's why you have a range to work with
okay so like i started to say a few
seconds ago
five seems to be a reasonable number for
maintenance even
individuals and we actually see if by
the way in some of my other videos i've
described this with endurance
things like vo2 max and metabolic
enzymes in the muscle tissue
same thing with hypertrophy they tend to
stay around pretty well with
just the lowest vol possible dose so
even as low as five cents per week is
probably enough to keep you at where
you're currently at
so for whatever reason you're injured or
busy week or something if you could just
get
a little bit even five sets in per week
you could probably stay
where you're at so hopefully that gave
you a little bit of context
um about where to where to go where to
look out for some of these things
keep in mind we are still missing a lot
of research especially at the end
at the end of the spectrum here there's
no resell research out there again like
i said past 25 or 30.
a former um intern of mine lauren
calenzo symbol has done a great job with
with some
with one summoning workout here but we
need more research especially with the
high
highly trained folks to really figure
out does that taper at the end happen do
they actually start to get worse results
what exactly is going on there maybe you
can get around that by just eating more
calories
a lot of questions we necess don't
necessarily know at this point so
while you can i guess to summarize
untrained folks maybe
can get away with up to 20 cents per
week and train folks maybe 25.
um you gotta you gotta balance that with
how much they can actually recover right
so maybe you can do it for one week
and maybe you can get by into two weeks
but can you sustain that for six months
even if you're in you're periodizing so
you may wanna say this is possible but
i don't necessarily need to go to this
end you're gonna have to figure that out
kind of on your own so like i said we're
missing some research out there
i'll keep point to hyper tree then you
do want to balance your volume with
fatigue right so we've talked about this
in the intro but fatigue is the big
player here
so don't overshoot too soon i guess
that's one way i'll say
i really think a really a great article
i would recommend you go check out is by
my friend mike izutel
him and his co-authors of course james
and jared fantastic company i joked
about this
in the outline about how renaissance
prioritization is an organization this
company is just awful and why they're
stupid
i was being completely facetious i fully
support everything they're doing and
i wanted to promote them here because
they do such good work in this
so uh mike wrote at least first authored
this article training volume landmarks
for growth
and he does a really nice job of talking
about the difference between identifying
your own personal volume for both
maintenance
both for for maintenance what he calls
the minimum effective dosage so what you
have what's a minimum you have to do to
still get results
and your maximal recovery volume so in
other words if you did a little bit more
this would be pushing past that limit of
volume and while you might have gotten
more
you're going to compromise unduly your
recovery
so in the long run your total volume
would probably lose because you couldn't
get recovered enough
so he has these fancy acronyms from mev
and mar and things like this
we don't have the time to get into those
level of detail here but i would
encourage you to go check this stuff out
the method he uses to help you identify
this on your own
is very simple and i think very very
solid so
again different ranges of volume
depending on different
goals maintaining what you can minimum
effective or
you're trying to really push the limit
you want to hit that fence but not go
totally over and past that uh maximum
volume
when it comes to intensity i i kind of
mentioned this but
hey it's idiot proof right hypertrophy
training is
is hard to mess up is what i mean by
that and that's because of this
if you look across the literature
there's a nice review article in the
last couple years that came out
you see pretty much equal growth in
terms of muscle size
in a range of about 30 all the way up to
85 or maybe even slightly higher of your
one rep max
so what's this tell you intensity is
just a tool
that you can use to help you get one of
those three major stimuli
right stress tension or damage
so as long as you take these to the same
total amount
of volume especially volume load credit
at the end of the week
this gives you a lot of wiggle room to
play with you can do a lot of different
things here
volume or hypertrophy can be equal
across basically the entire loading
range
now it is pretty clear below 30 percent
starts to really compromise muscle gain
so you want to make sure you probably
hit that number i personally almost
always go at least 40 to 50 percent
very rarely do i recommend that that low
percent but you can in theory
what matters here is this you know
intensity
can't be screwed up as long as you're
going to basically failure or close and
you're hitting your volume
so at this point you have to make sure
that
you're considering other adaptations so
while say training at 30
may give you equal hypertrophy it
certainly will not give you equal
strength gains
so if you have an individual who is
truly trying to maximize hypertrophy
you're a jared feathers type just a hulk
of a guy and you really just
invested in two three four years of
growing as much as you can
well then it's probably fine to spend a
lot of time doing 30
only because you don't really care about
getting stronger or maybe you're going
through at least to say
a small phase a four week or an eight
week block
where you're not totally worried about
maximizing strength but you want to do
some lower load
training to get your volume up and it
wraps up and all that or for
any a number of reasons okay fine but if
you have a client company saying hey i
want to get bigger i want to get
stronger
or say you have an athlete in the off
season or you have a youth individual
who
needs just all these general physical
attributes well then i would caution you
against spending
all of your time not using any
i mean just all or a majority of your
time at that really low end of the
spectrum
because you're going to get equal
hypertrophy but you will not get any if
hardly any strength gains so you may
want to hedge your weight a little bit
up
as a general recommendation for most
people most of the time i say play with
the whole spectrum
do stuff some stuff at 30 40 50 67 80 90
leave in play right if you do that and
you're kind of uh touching
the whole thing you're going to end up
with a nice amount of hyper fiance
strength okay but think about this in
the context of your client your
situation
what are their goals what other factors
is what i always like what's the context
of the situation what else is going on
do they not recover from heavy loads do
they hurt their low back when they do
that does it
aggravate their elbows more do they hate
heavy lifting do they hate light lifting
and you can kind of play and you know
okay i can work around my clients goals
desires and preferences
and still be doing evidence-based
practice because i know i'll have the
same amount of growth
at the end so that being said
okay maybe i should have said this at
the beginning 30 40
only works if you're taking it to pretty
close to failure so surely if you're
doing
40 of your 100 max and you do three sets
of three
at a normal tempo that's not going to be
heavy enough to induce mechanical
tension it's not going to cause any
damage and there will be no metabolic
stress
so you can expect almost no hypertrophy
so implicit in this slide is the
assumption that you're taking this
to failure or close so let's talk more
specifically about what that means to
actually take to failure
right because we have to consider some
things if
if we're going all the way say at this
high end of the spectrum
85 percent and we're taking it to
maximal volume
or to magnet to maximum volume are we
compromising fatigue are you either
getting extremely damaged
for example uh you could do sets
to total failure at 30 percent and
you're going to get very little damage
you'll get a good burn but you're not
going to get extremely sore
you take 85 percent up to those maximum
repetitions
multiple days a week you're going to get
burned down from that very quickly
and so again that's another factor to
consider
is what am i going after what else is
going on and what do i mean when i say
truly taking to failure so brad did a
nice job of summarizing this
uh in an article here for the strength
and conditioning journal through the
nfca
if you remember all these things are
free brad and many others write just
extensive amounts of articles these are
not really research articles they're
very practitioner based
they summarize the research for people
like you so if you're enjoying this
video you probably love the strength
finishing journal by the nsca
and here's what brown said basically
when we say failure we don't really mean
true maximal failure i'm not going to
walk you through this figure but i
wanted to show it to you hit pause
read it on your own if you like he
explains in more detail
but i'm going to skip past and sort of
summarize and he basically says this
based on the available evidence you can
take it to a couple of reps
shy of failure and still get maximal or
the same amount of gains it doesn't seem
to be any advantage to taking yourself
to a true
true failure again we're talking about
specifically when we're looking for
muscle hypertrophy
and so we need more research in this
area but the folks at renaissance
periodization mike
and stuff would call this reps in
reserve or
so mike says hey all right you can use
failure
especially for other adaptations but
stay focused on maximizing muscle growth
so you can use it but you just need to
use it sparingly because those last
couple of reps
take an exceptionally high amount of
fatigue
or recoverability out of us and so let's
say
you're doing three sets of ten and you
get to rep eight and you know like
you're like you're smoked but you think
like you can just turn around mentally
you can go full just bore and you can
get those last two reps out
maybe it probably maybe you could but
was it really worth it because now next
time you go to train
did you lose maybe three or four reps
because you had to go to such a level
for those last two that it took so many
resources out of you
that next time you had to stop at six
and so you got 10 and 6
16. if you would have stopped at 8 here
and 8 there you could also got
16 or maybe you could have gone nine
here and nine here
and you could actually get more total
volume so that's when we talk about
saying
not to absolute failure the general
number that you'll see is anywhere
between
four or less reps in reserve so again if
you think 10 is like
what you could absolutely got if you
just you know had as much no explode as
you could
sniff some some smelling salts and you
just lit them up
that means you got to get to at least
six if you stop at five
that's not close enough to failure eight
is probably the magic number in this
equation which would be two reps in
reserve okay
so at least leave one in the tank
probably two at
maximum four though okay
you could also go through small periods
say a day a week maybe even a few
several weeks
three weeks four weeks of you know
taking it to failure or close but you do
need to periodize it then right so
it's gonna have to back off a little bit
the next couple of weeks if you do that
you can use it
more appropriately or like i said any
other combination of restricting
the failure training to true failure to
certain days for weeks or workouts so
if it's a mondays or or my go days so no
matter what i'm going to get after it
always on mondays or sundays or
saturdays or whatever
so it's like a once a week where you
know you're going to go after it that's
probably fine
or certain workouts or something i like
how kenny kane
does this um at oak park
his gym in santa monica where he
basically says 10
of your training can can take you here
and so if you train four times a week
over the course of the month that's four
times four would be 16 workouts 10
of that would be something like one to
two workouts a month where you can just
let it all go
it does not it doesn't mean they're easy
the rest of them look but the rest of
them would stop at eight
or lower but you get two workouts a
month where you can just let it fly
i think that makes a ton of sense for
most people right if you're really
really into it maybe a third workout
if you're young maybe that third workout
maybe a fourth which would be once a
week if you're a little bit older maybe
that's
once a month is good where you really
take it to that place i know honestly
personally with my
professional fighters uh i like to take
them to that
what they would usually say dark place
no more than about once a month and
we'll take them close a lot
but there's one time when i'm going to
really push into that
something happen in your brain here
thing but you really can't get
away with more than once or twice a
month period even with those folks and
their recovery is
extremely high in those folks
okay i think i've made my point here so
let's move on to our next
variable that will influence both volume
and intensity and that's your rest
intervals right so this is the rest you
take per set obviously if you take a
longer rest
that will enable you to either do more
total repetitions
the next set or higher load okay
if you do shorter the inverse happens
well which one is better
a nice review article again in the last
couple of years has come out
and basically said either one now i know
brad
brad schoenfeld is is basically hedging
his bets towards he thinks actually
longer rest intervals more like two to
three minutes
in between your sets is actually better
because it's gonna allow more work at a
higher intensity
but the research right now in fairness i
think says it's about equal
okay maybe a slight hedge towards longer
rest intervals
to me again this means either one's
totally fine
make your decision based on context of
course shorter rest intervals
mean you're going to have more fatigue
but you're not going to have the
intensity or the load
so you could probably do it more
frequently higher rest intervals mean
you're going to be heavier you do more
reps
i think the longer term recovery is
maybe a little bit lower
okay i personally use a variation
use it both do some of your workouts
with 30 seconds to rest
okay you're going to end up basically
being in massive metabolic stress and
the burn the pump
like crazy then i do some when i have up
to five minutes of rest and i really
just go heavy
for my tens so this could look like
something if you're doing squats for a
set of 10
on your short rest interval day you're
gonna do four sets 30 seconds rest you
might tap out at 200 pounds
you you might barely be able to finish
your four set with 200 pounds
the exact same workout now just by
giving yourself four minutes rest in
between set
you might finish at 240. right you could
be a really big difference and that's
quite a
big difference in in what you actually
gave your body it's a stimulus that's
um quite different all right third time
in a minute say the same thing
you get the idea okay so that being said
then that will help us kind of lead into
frequency
which is how many days per week and a
couple of nice review articles you got
two to pick from there
again brad you know it's just such an
up-and-coming young scientist he is
in this field contributed and it looks
honestly pretty clear that
frequency doesn't significantly impact
hypertrophy when volume is equated
so if you want to work a muscle out once
per week twice per week three times per
week as long as you get the same numbers
by the end of the week month
it's probably going to be pretty similar
now personally
i will argue unless you're in some
special circumstances one day per week
per muscle is not a good strategy
i just struggle to believe you will
consistently be able to put up the
intensity and the volume on one day that
you could do in at least two days
use example i said earlier five sets
monday five sets thursday
that means you gotta do ten cents per
day now ten sets per muscle group is not
particularly hard
let's imagine you did three sets of ten
of squats counted that for your quads
three sets of ten of leg press
quads three sets of ten leg extensions
so you squatted leg press and leg etc
that's not that crazy of a day and
that's nine cents right there at ten
right like
you if you did that heavy you'd be
smoked but it's not
absurd to get to right the problem is
when you're trying to get to that 20 25
cents per
muscle per week i just i don't really
honestly think you can get there
most people could get there and once per
week so
whether you want to go past three times
per week uh we don't have a lot of
research on like four or five six micro
dosing type of stuff or hypertrophy
um i i would i would struggle to think
you'd be able to recover enough so i
honestly do think
probably two to four days a week mostly
two to three
probably mostly three is a really good
spot uh two would be just fine if you're
training your ass off like if you're
really getting after it
you might need that extra recovery and
you might be just fine there
so again kind of do what you feel is
best based on your context in your
situation
like i said it is easier to hit the
higher volumes with higher frequencies
so
pay attention to that in terms of the
exercise order so which ones to do first
now when we typically talk about this we
say things like okay
do your complex fast multi-joint
exercises
first in your workout and then finish
with your accessory
or auxiliary or whatever other term
people like to use for these
supplemental things at the end so
you would do bench and you would do your
pull-ups and lap poles and
bent row and all these big things and
you would eventually work yourself down
to tricep kickbacks
and say external rotations and then
hammer curls and all these single joint
things
well if you're just looking for
hypertrophy it probably doesn't matter
if you start with the single joint stuff
and then work your way to the multijoint
you're not really worried about the
quality of the work output you're
worried about getting to a certain level
of fatigue and tension so
i don't think it really matters and in
fact if again you look at an article
that came out just at the end of
february here
the review article is it's going to say
the same thing basically either one is
acceptable to do
i still prefer honestly multi-joint
first
for a whole host of practical reasons
but you have the bandwidth to use
whichever one you'd like so talking a
little bit more about the exercise
choice
if you've seen any one of any of my
previous videos i like to hammer these
concepts that exercises themselves
do not determine the adaptation so you
can't say oh i'm trying to get my legs
bigger
so i'm going to do these exercises okay
what determines
your legs getting bigger is the
application like we've just spent 20
minutes talking about it's the volume
it's the reps right it's all those
things that determine what outcome you
get
the exercise determines only the
movement plane you're in
right so frontal sagittal rotational uh
the muscles and joints that are likely
but no guarantee
to be used the contraction type right
was an eccentric first and then a
concentric
was it concentric and eccentric it's
isometric like
whatever the muscle is doing the
contraction type and then the technical
proficiency so what i mean by that is
let's say you had two individuals and
they're both trying to grow their
glutes and you had them both do a back
squat well if one of them does a very
high bar
vertical back squat and the other one
does a more power lifting style low bar
well the muscles they're using quote
unquote in the
even just looking at their own body
length right even if they both squatted
the same style
but one has a really long torso and
short femurs in the opposite
one has great ankles one has a more open
hip depending on their technical
proficiency
that will determine in large part what's
actually happening
so you really really have to think past
this idea of
okay i'm going to pick the exercises
i want based on either the movement
pattern i want to get
or the muscle now typically for the
other
strength tanning outcomes so strength
power speed
we tell people oh don't pick by muscles
pick the exercises you do in your
workout
by the movement pattern so do a
horizontal row
do a hip hinge do a vertical press
right with with again programming for
performance you rarely pick by the
muscle
when we get to hypertrophy though people
always like to say oh okay now i pick by
the muscles so you go do your workouts
people like to do body part splits which
means they're picking their
exercise by the muscle they want to work
so today is a bicep day
right today is a quad day it's not a leg
press day it's a quad day
well if you look at the research it's
going to show you
the evidence is actually pretty similar
between
training by movement pattern and
training by picking the muscle
for hypertrophy so you can do either of
these approaches and have
equal results now i have nothing against
picking by muscle especially if you have
a client who has a specific desired
outcome
i want my glutes to get bigger you
better damn well pick
several glute exercises right i want to
make sure my shoulders get bigger
make sure you're not just like well no
we do horizontal pressing no like do
something where they go oh yeah
i feel that right there on my shoulder
perfect okay
i just want to make sure you you realize
that you're not forced
to pick by the muscle for hypertrophy
the research would suggest
equal outcomes equal amount of growth at
picking one
versus the other okay so you want to
make sure you're you're balancing this
equation here of what i call order
versus chaos
so on one end of the say order spectrum
imagine going and doing the exact same
muscle of the exact same
lips every single time even for saying
eight week or ten week block
well the beauty of that is you get you
make sure that that
muscle in that range of motion gets
trained
the downside is what if it's only
working this part of the bicep or this
part of the deltoid not this part of the
deltoid
by having more chaos in other words more
variation in your exercise choice
you're more likely to get more rounded
results but you're less likely to get
actual results because
you're never stimulating the muscle in
the same spot
and so less total work happens there let
me give you a tangible equation
let's say you have two individuals and
you're gonna do the bench press
and you do the bench press and the next
day you're like man my
pecs are so sore and my front delts are
sore
and i say really i don't even feel it in
my pecs it's all my
triceps oh my gosh my triceps and my
elbows are crushed
well if we both just continue to do the
same variation
you're gonna wonder why i don't grow any
pecs and you don't grow any triceps
or whatever the thing is right and so if
we said okay great
mondays we do this style of benching
and we fill it in our triceps more
wednesday we're going to
rotate our hands and use dumbbells
instead of a barbell or we're gonna use
a little bit of an incline
or we're going to use a different swiss
bar and now all of a sudden i start
feeling in different part of the muscle
well if you only do the exact same
exercise variation every time
and say that exercise variation really
lit your pecs on fire well i promise you
in eight weeks you would see growth in
your pecs
but if you didn't ever see it fill in
your triceps then the triceps maybe
weren't going to get anything or the
inverse if you were the other example
however if every single time you went in
you did a slightly different variation
you might not see much growth anywhere
because okay today's variation got my
picks but tomorrow's didn't
and then the third one i did didn't
either and the fourth one kinda did
and by the time you came back for your
fifth workout which is now three weeks
later
you've only actually stimulated the pec
once every three weeks
and maybe the pec really only got eight
ten sets per week kind of at most
so you're not going to really get a
specific area of growth so you want to
use both of these things appropriately
all right and so we've kind of talked
about this right or i did at the
beginning or
sorry you weren't here for the beginning
i talked about this in part one
of the three part muscle physiology
series here that there's not uniform
growth of the muscle and one of the
reasons i believe this happens is
because when we do studies
we will pick one specific variation and
everyone in the study
for the entire time gets that variation
for scientific reasons we have to do
that because we have to have control
but i'm not surprised when you say okay
we're all doing preacher curls for eight
weeks
and then we go look at the muscle and we
don't have uniform growth
here here and here in all parts well you
only do one variation and it probably
targeted that part of the muscle
a lot more than somebody else so i think
this is actually a flaw
that we need to do we actually would be
interesting maybe a nice little masters
project or
a dissertation to do things where you
look at
slight variations of a single movement
uh across one muscle and see if that
actually holds true because we need more
research on this to clarify what exactly
happens
throughout the entire muscle right so
we're not exactly sure
um especially for muscles that cross
multiple joints so
here's where this gets really
complicated
we know that from an emg perspective
this idea of non-uniform growth probably
makes sense
so when we look at things we say okay
look
people that do a preacher curl and we
put emg which is a
sense little senses sensors on your arm
and tells me what part of your arm is
working
now it's not highly correlated with
what's actually going to grow
but it does give us some insight in
saying okay when i do this variation it
works as part of the muscle when i do
this variation it works another part
so while we haven't seen this idea bore
out in long-term research a lot
the acute emgs information says okay
different slight different variations
probably give you different parts of the
muscle that are working
we know this has been true and say the
practitioners for decades right anyone
has competed in fitness and figure
you don't just do one bicep curl or one
type of trisem you probably do three or
four
and you probably felt it right and
you're like oh my gosh you did this type
of
tricep and it works through there when i
do this type it's more up by the
shoulder
so you've felt this before we've seen
this in the emg research
we've seen this a little bit in the long
term hypertrophy research so
i think it's a probably safe assumption
that
like this is really happening so where
you really need to pay attention to
are your muscles that cross multiple
joints now if this is your first time
with anatomy
this is a challenge to go learn some
okay but you need to pay attention to
those muscles and there's only a few of
them right we got the shoulder elbow
hip knee and ankle and the example i
could give you would be
say the quadricep okay the quad is four
muscles of course they come together
into patella potential
crosses the knee inserts on the lower
part
of you right so when any quad muscle
contracts it pulls the patella and
extends the ear leg up
well all four of the quads cross the
knee joint but only one
crosses into the hip joint okay so when
the hip is
flexed okay up like that this means
three of those quads that start up here
high in my thigh
don't really care right they're still
going to extend the knee but the one
that crosses my hip joint is now
shortened because i've made the distance
between my hip
and my femur closer together that
significantly influences its ability to
contract
so you have to make sure in this
particular case if you want to optimize
your quad growth
that you're doing across the knee type
of quad training and across the hip
type of quad training where this really
starts to pay dividends
is the hip extensors right a lot of you
have done rdls i know you have
and you've seen how if you do them and
you feel them kind of in your butt high
up in the back side where you sit
high up in your middle or your hamstring
but you generally don't feel it across
your knee joint
well if you want to optimize hamstring
growth you probably need to do something
to where the hip range of
the hamstring is being challenged as
well as the knee range
of the hamstring and that will almost
never come from the exact same exercise
and the research on the hamstring is
starting to show that that's pretty
clear you probably
need to supplement hamstring curls or
something else
anyone who's ever done nordic curls or
things like that have felt that
um keep your hip extended if you wanna
if you hinge your waist and do it you're
gonna feel it across the hip joint if
you extend your
your hip and keep it there you're going
to feel it across the knee joint with
the rdl variation
same thing lock your knees out keep your
knees really locked out you're going to
wake up the next day
feeling like you tore your hamstring
behind your knee because they'll be so
damn sore
right so we need to make sure that with
our exercise variation we're paying
attention to again the muscles that
cross
multiple joints okay bicep curl
bicep curl tricep kickback tricep
kickback
and i do different things i'll give you
an example
uh take a look at this machine here i
took this with my camera
in houston texas last year at like a
lifetime fitness there's two things
wrong with this picture
number one this is called a dorsiflexor
machine and again
anatomy buffs i'm not sure if you
remember what dorsiflexion is
but it ain't this number two it's
clearly a bent row machine that's
showing that it works your anterior
deltoid
which like i guess like i guess
but really this is supposed to be
anyways
off topic i know you're anatomy i guess
as well it's getting out there so here's
i'm going to show you an example okay
now i'm going to do some dead lifting
here and i'm wearing that funky gear you
have you seen in there
and that has emg software on it which
means it can tell what part of my body
is being contracted
and how much okay i got little shorts on
and a little shirt on
and i'm going to do so i should have
done rdls for this toy space i just did
some dead lifts
but i'm going to show you how even
though you program deadlift
it may not be working the muscle groups
that you think so traditionally when we
program a deadlift you think it's low
back
glutes and hamstrings okay great but
because
say i did this on purpose but say my
anatomy was a little bit different and
the way my technique was a little bit
different right this technical
proficiency point four
that when i do my deadlifts i don't feel
it there so if you continue to program
deadlifts for me and you wonder why my
glutes and hamstrings aren't growing
and my quads are you can pick what the
hell deadlifts don't work the quads
but they do if that's what i'm using so
you really have to pay attention to the
person
their anatomy their technique as well as
the feedback they're giving it
okay so watch on the screen
here you go can you tell what muscles
i'm using
see it down here now this is pretty hard
to do
but i'll zoom in and you can take a look
at the numbers
sorry give it some tech aha
look at that i'll try to get a little so
it's a little more clear
okay i know it's hard to see but 80
quads i'm only 50
hamstring 30 adductors and about 18
glutes so why would you expect my glutes
to grow there when they're not being
used
okay i'll go back and play it again so
you can watch the video again red is
deep activation blue is
kind of not being used and watch my
upper back i'm pulling good with my lats
and i'm just trying to keep my glutes as
dead as possible and squeezing
so basically what i'm doing is a knee
extension
rather than a hip extension so i'm
driving the barbell up in because it's
light it's easy for me to pull this off
i'm getting the barbell up again by
driving knee extension
and pulling with my lats rather than by
squeezing and hip
extending my hips with my glutes
so if you were to program that for me
you would need to then supplement that
and say okay hamstrings didn't really
get much there
glutes didn't get a lot we need to come
back and give him some glutes
uh some hip thrust or something like
that as well as say this little exercise
now this little exercise is that's real
speed i'm not slowing it down
i like this again for that cross the
knee joint
part of the hip extension it's very very
slow
and i'm trying to keep my glutes
extended i'm not letting them flex at
all though i'm
i'm losing position there because i was
pretty tired let's be real
but again you do that for you know a few
sets you're going to wake up with some
real sore
behind the knees or you're going to feel
like you're torn acl or something
all right so i think you're getting the
point all this is under the guise of
okay what exercise do i pick
we don't want to be too random or too
routine
we want to feel free to play with grip
more research has come out now on things
like foot stance so maybe when you're
doing your leg press
your toes are turned in maybe straight
forward maybe a little bit out
same thing with your deadlifts i
encourage you to play with your grip
neutral
right pronated supinated etc have some
intention and thought pay attention to
your anatomy
right when you actually rotate what
actually happens what am i trying to get
not just doing this
variation for the sake of variation but
we also don't want to just go in and
say that's the machines i use and i do
this machine i do this machine and i
don't change anything so going back to
the
our friends at renaissance periodization
and they're just idiotic
ideas and terrible systems
i think this is wonderful i encourage
you to use this on yourself as well as
your clients
ask three basic questions okay number
one do you feel a pump
all right if they say no i felt no pump
whatsoever give them zero points they
say okay it's okay one point if you're
like oh yeah
i got a great pump give them two now
this is specifically referring to the
muscle you're trying to target
not overall but hey we were trying to
get the triceps did you get a great pump
on the triceps
yes no great number two
how sore were you the next day not sore
at all
yeah i was sore for like a few hours but
once i got kind of going i loosened up
and i was fine or
man yeah i was pretty tight there for
two or three days two points and the
last question is
did you feel it in the targeted muscle
during the lift during the actual lift
itself
yes no or and oh yeah absolutely got
smoked
so you have three scores highest score
possibly six
lowest is zero and what mike is going to
tell you is
okay that total score should look like
something like this if it's between zero
to one it's probably ease too easy and
you're not going to have any gains you
may not even be able to maintain your
current level that's not enough stimulus
somewhere between two to four is enough
to cause gain and it's probably your
maintenance
volume but you probably need to get to
five to six
to really start to get closer to your
maximum recoverable volume
or optimizing your gains you do want to
pay attention though
remember we've talked about how uh
damage
doms is not great you don't want to just
chase more and more and more and more
damage there because eventually it's
going to bite you in the ass by taking
away your recovery and your fatigue
so five to six is probably the range
where you want to be really careful
if i'm being real four to five i think
is like the
perfect spot for most people with some
dabs into the six
but not too much okay really simple
system i think you could use with all of
your clients
really quickly great feedback i also
like sneakily sinclair i don't think so
i think it's great to just make sure
that you're getting feedback from your
clients
you want to get bigger here are you
feeling it there no okay i'm doing my
best to make sure i'm listening to you
and your concerns and we're going to get
you what you want
i'm telling you people lose a lot of
clients because they come in they like
they want their cast to be bigger
and they just don't ever feel their
calves getting worked so you need to
make sure that that actually happens
right now the last little piece here um
that we don't have time to get into is
and this is in mike's article that i've
referenced earlier but
if you really want to maximize your
hypertrophy in all of your muscles it
probably does require muscle specific
programming what i mean is
the optimal volume is not the same for
the triceps biceps quads hamstrings
the function and structure is too
different the way that the muscles
are running into the bones the fiber
type faster slow
the length it's totally different so you
probably do
need a total a different volume range
per week
for the calf that you do the deltoids i
didn't want to get into all that in this
video it's really
pretty long extensive but mike has that
up with some suggestions we don't have
research at that level
but mike just has used his years and
years of experience
a little bit of research to say here are
the numbers i think you should shoot for
um there but i feel like renaissance
position owes me some money for this
like what a bunch of free promo right i
don't even get like a plug or anything
from them
this guy i'm just kidding i love those
guys they do great stuff so i fully
support them
okay that being said uh kind of
continuing down this idea of how you can
modify the actual exercise it's the
range of motion
now your default setting and my opinion
should be taking through all your joints
through all the range of motion
what's that mean your shoulder can do
all of this stuff
so i believe in training you should do
all those things your hips knee and
ankle have a certain amount of flexion
so you should squat you should deadlifts
you should go through those full ranges
of motion
if you can do it in good position i
don't advocate anybody training in bad
position
bad position of any of the joints or the
spine is bad
so if you want to maximize your muscle
growth the default should be going all
the way up
and all the way down all the way up and
all the way down
most of the time if you have to lose
position
to get that full range of motion i don't
advocate that
okay but i also don't advocate doing all
your training
like this either and the research would
support me on that one
it's a it's equal if not a little bit
more growth per volume
with a full range of motion most of the
time okay
so again like everything else i
recommend doing a little bit of both
do some partial range of motion partial
repetition stuff the bulk of your
training the center of it should be full
range of motion
but feel free to add a little bit of
partial stuff in there every once in a
while
right but again same or more growth
for the same reps at the same weight by
just going more range of motion
that's what the research is going to
suggest and that just came out again in
the last few months
so in terms of the exercise type
concentric versus eccentric
you can see a nice little review from a
couple years ago out
and it looks like about equal with a
slight hedge towards eccentric growth
and i think i would honestly argue that
it i think the evidence for the
benefit of eccentrics over concentric is
stronger than the research shows
so what's that mean should you do
negatives
forced eccentrics i do think it's a good
part actually
for that token i think isometrics are
fantastic i think those should be a nice
part of your equation
do i think you need to do all of your
training c center no not even close most
of it
well i don't think most of it's
appropriate but i think you should spend
some time doing some specific eccentric
training
just be careful we know what that does
to damage we know that that has an
appreciable increase in soreness and
fatigue so
go slowly build it up but i think it's
probably a
really smart idea to add that to your
training and i'll say this so i don't
think people do enough
eccentric training okay it's probably
also pretty good at specifically
targeting the fast stretch fibers
those seem to really respond to it so
it's another way to get stimuli into
some tissue that maybe
isn't always getting it when you're
doing some other stuff like light
repetition or light load high repetition
training
okay so when you're doing it how fast
should you go i honestly don't think rep
tempo matters
at all for the most part we've seen the
research would suggest
equal growth with your repetition speed
so the time it takes you to complete
ranging from as little as half a second
so boom
pretty fast it'd be faster than that but
all the way up to eight seconds
okay now obviously the longer the
repetition takes the less total reps you
can do
this is akin to what some folks would
call time under tension
okay people in the field will say this
all the time oh it's about time under
tension hypertension
um it really isn't okay it's about
getting to some total volume
now it's difficult to to really equate
these things
but my point is use a combination again
if you're going to have equal results
why not use a combination
just like we've been saying all along
there's a difference between variation
and randomization randomization is
pulling random out of your hat
that's not intelligent program design
variation is having a plan
specific intent and a purpose
understanding the pros the cons what
just happened in your program
what's about to happen in your program
and then throwing some things in just
for the sake of
a little bit of randomness and some fun
okay last couple of ideas i want to
throw out common questions
we've heard this for many years in the
forums hey your growth hormone is
highest in the morning
your testosterone's high then so you
should train in the morning when those
are higher you'll get more gains
a really cool study by another author
you've seen
pulled up several times here at
australia and doing great work down
there
just published last year it doesn't seem
to matter at all whether you train in
the morning evening or afternoon again
just for the sake of maximizing
hypertrophy so do what fists fits your
day and your lifestyle
in your program so three last
concepts of program design variables and
then i want to hit you with some final
questions
to see about your comprehension of
learning so these are three different
items that have been shown to have some
effect
they're not the level where we have uh
like review articles on them
most of these have somewhere between
like one and three total papers
published
so don't ever get too excited about
these things until we have
in my opinion 10 or more studies or so
on a topic but
things like mid-set flexing so this is
you know you do your bicep curls then
you sit there and flex
has been shown to maybe have results in
additional muscle growth over not
flexing between that
pre-exhaustion so this is uh you know
again you do a bunch of tricep
extensions prior to hitting a bench
press
so smoke the triceps and then do your
bicep work
and then finally what they call the mind
muscle connection so this is
intentionally focusing on your bicep
when you're doing your curl
not just doing whatever work is needed
to lift that weight but trying to get
the maximal contraction
and feeling the connection there also
but potentially benefits are purchasing
more than not doing so
and all of these three things make total
sense because when we go back to the
fundamentals of what we're trying to do
let's go back to part two in this video
series
what stimulates the growth right the
exercise is just a
pseudo activation thing all you're
trying to do is create that stimuli
so if i can cause the muscle to work
harder it doesn't matter if i have a 10
pound or 100 pound
thing in my arm if i get the same level
of activation same level of fatigue
same level of contraction same level of
damage
right so don't get lost in the numbers
don't just be like well sets of this and
reps this
it's for hypertrophy it's all about
the quality of contraction if you're not
feeling it in the muscle group
you got to make a change right if you're
not
really paying attention whether you did
8 reps or 10 reps or 30 reps for that
matter it doesn't matter
the higher the quality the more results
so you got to really check in mentally i
give hyper entry training a bunch of
because it's super easy to program
for but that doesn't mean the workouts
are easy
you got to really check in mentally and
get the most out of every contraction
that's what separates people who gain a
lot from those who don't gain as much
okay
so let's put you to the test here a
little bit and see what happens in some
various scenarios let's imagine you're
going to do your workout
and you're like doug here then you're
going to do four sets of 10
at 300 pounds and you get to set three
and you're on rep seven and you realize
i don't know if i can finish these ten
and more importantly i know there's no
chance i can finish that fourth set
what should you do should you take some
weight off for the fourth set
so you can finish your 10 reps make sure
you leave the weight on
and finish heavy as you can and just
stop at six or
five or three reps or whatever you could
i know this has happened to you if
you've trained like this this has
happened
if it hasn't you're not you're probably
not trying hard enough
well in general the answer would be for
hypertrophy it doesn't matter either
one's fine
most of the time though we've talked
about how volume is the driver though
so i would generally recommend take the
weight off and make sure you hit your
volume
okay so you can make an argument for
intensity but most the time
volume would be our appropriate answer
here cut the intensity keep the volume
okay what happens if you screw up one or
more of those
modifiable variables so you did the
exercise order wrong
or you didn't hit your optimal volume or
you did the wrong
nothing nothing this is why
program programming is video proof
you're going to be just fine
this is not true for speed it's not true
for strength
uh for anaerobic endurance it's not true
for maximal orbital capacity training
if you screw up one of these cofor verb
there you might have ruined the
adaptation
or you might have given yourself a
different adaptation than what you're
looking for with hypertrophy
since you're just trying to get work
done as long as you took it to that
level it doesn't really matter here it's
not irrelevant but
the point is you can survive you can get
equal gains by doing something different
okay one of our last things here that i
want to get to is the hard gainers
now traditionally what we see here and
mike has done a great job at auburn
in the last couple of years trying to
identify the top responders from the
lowest responders and we're trying to
figure out biologically what's actually
happening there
well at this point we don't have strong
scientific evidence but i believe
it's pointing towards folks just need
different prescriptions
okay what research tells us is what's
most likely to work
best for most people so if you were to
take 100 people and put them in our
studies and do exactly what i just
showed you in the last
40 minutes here 80 or 70 percent
would have great gains some folks on the
end wouldn't it wouldn't be enough and
some folks would be too much
but that's when the art of coaching
comes in and that's why you friends
you're irreplaceable scientists i can
come and go you don't need me
i can't live without you though you got
to be able to pay attention to your
people
and be like yep you're a 70 percenter
just keep it going
you're a 15 or this is too much you're
15 of this is too little
so when you get a hard gainer and trust
me i've got one
over a year now professional athlete and
it's just a struggle to put on muscle
with him
all the resources in the world we get
everything checked you can imagine i
mean every day we track
everything so many things we spent so
much money on
measurement and you have no idea
we just have to play okay let's go
higher intensity lower volume
let's go way more volume until you can
find a spot and i promise you do that
with the assumption your sleep and your
food and all that's checked off right
you probably in my opinion just need
more volume
most hard responder hard gainers in my
experience
need more volume than the rest that
sucks it's not fair i get it
but that's usually your solution so we
tack on more volume and we see pretty
good results
okay to summarize kind of what we've
been over here
there are a few concepts you have to hit
to with hypertrophy training
the methods you use are basically
unlimited right so the concepts i'm not
going to walk you through because we've
been talking about it for 40 minutes
all right you know what to get to you
know how to do it in terms of methods
hey use that time under tension
isometrics as well
negatives eccentrics cool you like
pyramids and drop sets
all right all been shown to work in the
science
supersets blood flow restriction you
like to do some reps to failure at the
end i love that stuff
awesome the one kind of caveat i would
give you here is
i generally don't recommend doing weight
lifting movements this would be olympic
weightlifting or they're variations
for the sake of hypertrophy unless this
is your competitive sport
so we don't do three sets of 12 of
snatches
unless you're competing in that sport
right i'm talking if the goal is
hypertrophy
there's no rationale to do hang cleans
for twelves right pick a different
exercise for your quads or your glutes
or whatever else you're doing
uh the risk to reward ratio is just too
high
and it's not a main driver so we don't
go there
as well as plyometrics now the one
caveat i will say to this and why
plyos or asterisks is you actually will
get and the research will support this
a pretty decent amount of hypertrophy
from plyometrics they're incredibly
damaging though
so really be careful don't take someone
who hasn't worked out in three years and
haven't come in and have them start
doing box jumps
uh or lands or hurdle hops they're gonna
walk they're gonna be blown apiece
they're gonna be so damn sore they're
gonna be so much more sore than if you
had them do front squats
ten sets of ten all right so
you can use plyos if you are really
truly advanced both as a coach and an
athlete
if you're anywhere not that though i
generally say don't do plyos
for the purposes of hypertrophy okay
so if you are one of these folks like
this gentleman here and you're either
untrained
or you're kind of loosely trained i
recommend just hitting the four
following things
right build movement patterns and
technique invest in the long term it's
what my friend brian mckenzie and i
always call short game versus long game
so invest in the long term i'm not
worried about optimizing your results in
the next six weeks or six months i want
to build you so that six years from now
you're still training your ass off you
feel great and nothing hurts
right that typically means i'm gonna use
full range of motion multi-joint stuff
at controlled speeds
i'm not gonna go excessively low because
the damage might get there
and i may lose position slow excessively
slow i mean
but i can go slow stuff right i'm also
not going
out of control fast because they
probably don't know how to control that
in their ligaments and connective tissue
probably aren't ready for maximal speed
stuff
be consistent i mean honestly this is
probably the biggest one right you want
to build those habits you
just you wanted to be a part of their
life that four days a week they work out
and don't chase them off and lose them
because they're either being so sore
or you're not challenging them enough or
they're bored or whatever else
and then on that note progress them
slowly
okay six years 16 years not
six weeks from now okay you want in fact
my friend chad landers up here in la
uh man the guy's had several clients for
20 plus years now one of the most
successful personal trainers
out there chad's great um excellent
person to follow and pay attention to
but you know tell you you want to make
money you want to make money as a
personal trainer have 20-year clients
don't worry about maximizing your
results in eight weeks so that they'll
come
no these folks don't leave you kenny
kane the same way boy they don't leave
you for 20 years you're going to make
them
they're going to buy your house for you
basically so you do that when you
progress slowly
you can't stagnate but you don't want to
smash them either
if you're more like this then i
recommend
optimizing your volume so start tracking
that 20 to 25 weeks and start paying
attention do you respond better when
you're at 30
or 20. um you buy do some precise
programming have a specific plan laid
out
for one to six months don't program hop
okay don't do this guys
thing for three weeks and then this
guy's for two and then hey i'm gonna
take part of this guy's one and do half
of this one
don't do that really spend time
investing what works best for me
by doing one thing consistently for a
couple of months or even a year
um go ahead and get fancy start playing
with eccentrics and
and all this other stuff that we talked
about and then vary the stimuli
okay you don't honestly need that much
variation if you're kind of a newbie or
at the beginning but as you become more
trained you do need to change up the
exercise choice intensity volume
and things like that okay
so to finalize here
as i mentioned a few minutes ago
research
doesn't tell us individual programming
guidelines
it tells us what's most likely to work
for most people and that may or may not
work for you
so you really got to pay attention to
that now i will tell you i feel like
everyone i talk to feels like they're
the one percent
they're the one person that's not true
for when more likely you're the 99
so be more patient you're probably going
to respond just like everybody else did
but you do need to pay attention to
yourself and your clients right because
it's not necessarily
going to be optimal for you also don't
confuse what we call better with no
effect
so if if you looked at say the eccentric
training and it was five percent better
than concentric training that doesn't
mean the concentrating didn't work
so don't go around being like oh
concentric that's bro science it doesn't
work
no it does it just means this other
style worked a little bit better but
both did
and of all almost everything i've shown
you so far does work
it's just other things maybe work
slightly better
last point we have a good amount of
information a lot of the stuff i
presented to you today
covered untrained individuals and we
have more and more research especially
in the last three or four years
on well-trained or reasonably
well-trained by that that typically
means
a year of consistent training but i
wouldn't call these folks highly trained
in fact i feel like my standard in my
lab is pretty high for that
but a lot of other labs i'm like that's
well trained
six months of lifting and you lifted
once per week
i don't know so be cautious of that and
we certainly don't have any information
on
folks that are like ifbb pros and
definitely almost nothing
basically nothing on like world folks so
i don't know what's going to separate
you from being well trained to
getting your pro card i don't know
what's going to separate that from
winning a world title
we don't have any information there at
that point you're going to have to lean
on the coaches
the individuals have the actual
experience who put people on stage
who won medals so if they tell you
something that's contradictory to what i
said
i'm not going to say they're wrong now
if they're talking about best way to
train untrained folks or
kind of moderately well ones and then we
can have a discussion
i would like to think the research that
we've done at these first two levels
does inform the next
two or three but i don't know that for
sure
and you shouldn't either so what i
always say with in my video of
detection is the level of
confidence should match the level of
evidence
and since we have very little evidence
for the folks in categories three and
four here
i don't have a tremendous amount of
confidence in saying what will work
or won't work so to finish off here i
have a little bit of a challenge for you
i would love that if you try something
from this video that is new
so tell me your level of training and
then tell me what you tried so if you've
never done
you know training at 30 for a month give
it a go
if you've never done isometrics for
hypertrophy try it out
uh never done that hamstring curl
exercises pretty easy it's great for the
foot too by the way
i love it i would love to hear back um
maybe even i'll give a
special something or whatever to someone
who gives me the best one so uh
comments on the youtube of course and um
you know
kids in the class emails that's good
forum post i'm great with all that
um social media whatever but i want to
hear back on what you liked and what you
didn't like
this was a hell of a series this took me
probably two months to put together
i really hope you enjoyed it i love
strength training i love hypertrophy
i love every house of my job i hope you
can feel the passion i have for all this
stuff
i don't care at all if 30 people watch
these videos
because these 30 people you're my people
i love you
we'll see you around everyone
[Music]
you